Daf Peh Zayin דף פ"ז, Daf Peh Zayin, 87, and we pick
up in the middle of Peh Vav Amud Bet פ"ו עמוד ב'
Peh Vav Amud Bet and we're in the middle of these Agadetas
אגדתא Agadetas about Abraham and the angels and feeding them and the
feast because the Mishna משנה Mishna spoke about if you according to
one position in the Mishna משנה Mishna if you contracted to give
to feed your workers then that's an additional than the norm and
then you'd have to feed them almost an infinite amount because they're
the children of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. So that led to all
this discussion about the feast that Abraham prepared for the angels showing
how you know how elaborate it was or the food that Abraham
you know I guess gave to others and therefore the food that
Abraham's children would be deserving of if you made that type of
a if you contracted with them. So that's how we got there
but now we're in the middle of the whole discussion of Abraham
and the angels. So we pick up with the following. Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav. It is 1, 2,
3, 4, 5.
I'm sorry no I skipped excuse me three lines from the top.
Amar Rav Tanchum bar Chanilai אמר רב תנחום בר חנילאי. Amar Rav
Tanchum bar Chanilai. Three lines from where the lines get the widest,
the end of the line. Amar Rav Tanchum bar Chanilai le'olam al
yeshaneh adam min haminhag אמר רב תנחום בר חנילאי לעולם אל ישנה
אדם מן המנהג. Amar Rav Tanchum bar Chanilai le'olam al yeshaneh adam
min haminhag. A person should never change from the custom, which is
an interesting echo of the Mishna משנה Mishna of Hakol keminhag hamedina
הכל כמנהג המדינה, Hakol keminhag hamedina, which is talking about how the
norms of the society determine the parameters of a contract.
So in the same idea of the Minhag מנהג Minhag here but
it means when you go to a place, you know when in
Rome, what does it act like the Romans? Do as the Romans
do. So act according to the practices of the place. Sheharei Moshe
ala lamarom שהרי משה עלה למרום. Sheharei Moshe ala lamarom. When Moshe
went up to heaven velo achal lechem ולא אכל לחם velo achal
lechem he didn't eat bread, right? It says lechem lo achal umayim
lo shata לחם לא אכל ומים לא שתה lechem lo achal umayim
lo shata just like the angels. Umalachei Hasharet yardu lemata ומלאכי השרת
ירדו למטה Umalachei Hasharet yardu lemata when the heavenly angels came below
vayochlu lechem ויאכלו לחם vayochlu lechem and they ate bread because it
says you know Abraham fed them and they ate. So the Gemara
asks achlu salka dachatcha אכלו סלקא דעתך achlu salka dachatcha is that
really possible that they ate? You know it's not in their nature,
it's not possible. Ela eima nir'u kemi she'achlu veshata אלא אימא נראו
כמי שאכלו ושתו, Ela eima nir'u kemi she'achlu veshata, it would look
like they were eating but at least they made it look you
know they were respectful of the customs. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, kol ma
she'asa Avraham lemalachei hasharet be'atzmo כל מה שעשה אברהם למלאכי השרת בעצמו
kol ma she'asa Avraham lemalachei hasharet be'atzmo whatever however Abraham attended to
the heavenly angels himself personally, asa Hakadosh Baruch Hu levanav be'atzmo עשה
הקדוש ברוך הוא לבניו בעצמו asa Hakadosh Baruch Hu levanav be'atzmo God
repaid this by directly taking care of his descendants of Abraham's descendants
of Bnei Yisrael. Vechol ma she'asa Avraham al yedei shaliach וכל מה
שעשה אברהם על ידי שליח Vechol ma she'asa Avraham al yedei shaliach
and everything that Abraham did through a messenger, through an intermediary, so
asa Hakadosh Baruch Hu levanav al yedei shaliach עשה הקדוש ברוך הוא
לבניו על ידי שליח asa Hakadosh Baruch Hu levanav al yedei shaliach
so God took care of the descendants of Bnei Yisrael also through
an intermediary. So let's take a look. Nice little matching of psukim
פסוקים psukim here. El habakar ratz Avraham אל הבקר רץ אברהם. El
habakar ratz Avraham. Abraham ran to the cattle to get a cattle
to serve the angels. Veruach nasa me'et Hashem ורוח נסע מאת השם
Veruach nasa me'et Hashem so a wind came it says directly from
God and that gathered up the slav שלו, slav, the quail, so
that's gathering up meat. So the gathering of the meat. Vayikach chem'a
vechalav ויקח חמאה וחלב. Vayikach chem'a vechalav. He took the butter and
the milk. So hineni mamtir lachem lechem min hashamayim הנני ממטיר לכם
לחם מן השמים hineni mamtir lachem lechem min hashamayim I God directly
will bring down bread from heaven. So there it is God directly.
Now what does it have to do with butter and milk? So
I think it's a play on words because the word chem'a חמאה
chem'a and lechem לחם lechem okay so you have that and also
chalav חלב chalav two of the letters of the word chalav חלב
chalav are lechem לחם lechem right? L-Ch-M so I think that's what
we're doing here. Okay. Vehu omed aleihem tachat ha'etz והוא עומד עליהם
תחת העץ Vehu omed aleihem tachat ha'etz and Abraham stood under the
tree and attended to them. So hineni omed lefanecha sham al hatzur
הנני עומד לפניך שם על הצור hineni omed lefanecha sham al hatzur
I God will stand by you by the rock. Okay. But of
course the part there it's about and there ultimately it's about providing
water to the people so the same way here Abraham was standing
there and you know attending to their needs as they were eating.
Ve'avraham holech imam leshalcham ואברהם הולך עמם לשלחם Ve'avraham holech imam leshalcham
Abraham attended them to send them off. Vahashem holech lifneihem yomam והשם
הולך לפניהם יומם Vahashem holech lifneihem yomam God would walk in front
of them by day. So it's with them in front of them
but nevertheless attending them and seeing them on their way.
That's what Abraham did by himself. Now what did he do through
an intermediary? Yukach na me'at mayim יוקח נא מעט מים. Yukach na
me'at mayim. Let let some water be taken. Yukach na יוקח נא
Yukach na so he's not taking it. Let some water be taken.
So vehikita batzur veyatz'u mayim mimenu veshata ha'am והכית בצור ויצאו מים
ממנו ושתה העם
vehikita batzur veyatz'u mayim mimenu
veshata
ha'am so Moshe you hit the rock and you bring the water
out to the people. That's the same example as the tzur צור
tzur but what does God is standing there being present for the
people like Abraham was standing there the other is the actual bringing
of the water which is what Moshe did the same way Abraham
had somebody else bring the water. Upliga deRabbi Chama bar Chanina ופליגה
דרבי חמא בר חנינא. Upliga deRabbi Chama bar Chanina. Now this this
linking up of these psukim פסוקים psukim argues on Rabbi Chama bar
Chanina. Damar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina vechen tana devei Rabbi Yishmael דאמר
רבי חמא בר חנינא וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Damar Rabbi Chama
bar Chanina vechen tana devei Rabbi Yishmael. Beschar shlosha zachu lishlosha בשכר
שלושה זכו לשלושה Beschar shlosha zachu lishlosha for the merit of three
things that Abraham did the children merited three things. Beschar chem'a vechalav
zachu laman בשכר חמאה וחלב זכו למן Beschar chem'a vechalav zachu laman
for the butter and the milk they merited for the manna. Again
it's an interesting connection what does the chem'a חמאה chem'a and the
chalav חלב chalav have to do with the manna but again I
think it's the lechem לחם lechem play on words. Rabbi Chama רבי
חמא. Rabbi Chama. Oh that's an interesting point I didn't catch that
there was a Rabbi Chama רבי חמא Rabbi Chama there.
That's very good. Also bachama בחמא bachama chem'a חמאה. chem'a. Okay. Beschar
vehu omed
בשכר והוא עומד. Beschar vehu omed. עליהם, aleihem, Abraham attending to them,
זכו לעמוד ענן, zachu le-amud anan, the pillar of smoke. Now that's
just, so the only difference here is that it's not the same
match-up. Before we had Abraham stood and attended to them and God
stood by the rock, and here Abraham stood and the standing and
attending to them is matched by the pillar of the cloud. Okay.
יוקח נא מעט מים, yukkach-na me'at-mayim, let a little water be taken,
זכו לבארה של מרים, zachu le-be'erah shel Miriam, the well of Miriam,
which is, you know, the smiting of the rock which brings forth
the water, according to חז"ל, Chazal, that was the ongoing, that was
the באר be'er of Miriam. So therefore that is matched up although
it's describing it differently. So it was only a question of how
you matched up the standing, was the standing matched with God's standing
by the rock, providing the water, which is I guess more closely
connected to Abraham attending to them while they were eating, or to
the pillar of cloud which led them. Okay.
יוקח נא מעט מים, yukkach-na me'at-mayim, now we're going to go and
דרשן darshan the פסוקים, pesukim, you know, פסוק pasuk by פסוק, pasuk,
we're going to elaborate on the פסוקים. pesukim. יוקח נא, yukkach-na, some
of this what we might say might be familiar to you from
רש"י Rashi on the תורה, Torah, who quotes a lot of this,
or maybe the גמרא Gemara got it from רש"י, Rashi, I don't
know, okay so that's a joke. יוקח נא מעט מים. yukkach-na me'at-mayim.
Okay, so יוקח נא מעט מים ורחצו רגליכם, yukkach-na me'at-mayim ve-rachatzu ragleichem,
so let some water be taken and wash your feet, okay. So
אמר רבי ינאי ברבי ישמעאל, Amar Rebbi Yannai be-Rebbi Yishmael, אמרו לו,
amru lo, they said to him,
וכי בערביים חשדתנו, ve-chi be-aravayin chashadetanu, do you think we're Arabs, שהם
משתחווים לאבק רגליהם, she-hem mishtachavim le-avak ragleihem, that bow down to the
dust on their feet? I mean רש"י Rashi quotes this, I never
understood what חז"ל Chazal were responding to, did they really think that
the Arabs, you know, prayed to the dust on their feet? I
mean they prostrated on the ground. I never really understood what phenomenon
that was responding to. Also I wonder, pre-Mohammed,
what was the religion of Arabs? Does anybody know?
They were idolaters, they were idolaters, you know, פסל pesel worshipping tribes.
Okay. So
his religious revolution was to make them monotheists.
Okay, so they were basically your standard idolatrous pagans.
Right. They have a note.
Yeah, what does the note say? I mean I question Artscroll's historical
accuracy, but let's hear the note.
This is from מהר"ל Maharal in the second
explanation or... Yeah, yes, Avram's era were a nomadic people, traveled frequently,
they worshiped the god of the roads and thus used the dust
of their feet, a residue of the roads as something to which
they should bow down.
Okay, so that's interesting. I don't know if it's historically accurate, but
it's interesting that they're, I mean I did that the fact that
they're also a traveling nomadic things means that somehow, yeah. It is
funny sometimes, I don't know which, where it is, I think somewhere
on the New Jersey Turnpike when you're driving, they have some statue
there, about, you know what it is? About some something about I
don't know some saint of the highways or saint of the travelers,
anyway, alright.
There's one in Maryland too.
Oh, maybe that's what I'm thinking about. I'm thinking about Maryland, anyway,
alright. So fine, they worship the dust of their feet, maybe because
they worship the god of the travels or of the roads. Anyway,
so is that what you think, because you need us to wash
our feet? It's so funny they interpreted it that way. Maybe he
just wanted like, you know, if you're weary, you know, and your
feet have been walking on whatever, you know, it's a way of
rejuvenating. So anyway, do you think we're Arabs? שהם משתחווים לאבק רגליהם?
she-hem mishtachavim le-avak ragleihem? כבר יצא ממני ישמעאל. kevar yatza mimeni Yishmael.
So they said, you know, Yishmael is your descendant. He, you know,
so... וירא אליו השם באלוני ממרא. va-yera elav Hashem be-elonei Mamre.
Okay, okay so okay I guess that's the end of that story.
Traveling in a...
He was traveling in a... Oh, Rebbi Yishmael.
Oh, that's also an interesting point. It was אמר רבי ינאי ברבי
ישמעאל. Amar Rebbi Yannai be-Rebbi Yishmael. But that's interesting, but רש"י Rashi
says, but but here Yishmael is used as an insult where רש"י
Rashi would say כבר יצא ממנו kevar yatza mimenu is like a
respectful but רש"י Rashi says ממך יצא, mimcha yatza, הרגיל לעשות כן.
ha-ragil la'asot ken.
It's your descendant that worships idolatry, you know, that's the Arab and
the pagan. That's not us. So it's a good point that it's
a Rebbi Yishmael, the son of Rebbi Yishmael who says this, and
it's Yishmael that's being pegged with it. Alright, but anyway, somehow interestingly
the story just abruptly like stops there. He has no response. Alright
then, so whatever. I don't get what to do with it because
clearly that wasn't his intent and clearly it didn't have to be
interpreted that way.
Anyway, foot washing is a big deal in some Christendoms. What? Foot
washing.
Foot washing, well that's true. וירא אליו השם באלוני ממרא. va-yera elav
Hashem be-elonei Mamre. So now we're going to double back and start
at the beginning of the story. God appeared to him in אלוני
ממרא. Elonei Mamre. והוא יושב פתח האוהל כחום היום. ve-hu yoshev petach
ha-ohel ke-chom ha-yom. He was sitting by the door, by the opening
of the tent by the heat of the day. מאי כחום היום?
mai ke-chom ha-yom? What does it mean the heat of the day?
אמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא, Amar Rebbi Chama be-Rebbi Chanina, אותו היום
יום שלישי של מילה של אברהם היה. oto ha-yom yom shelishi she-milah
shel Avraham hayah. It was the third day of Avraham's ברית מילה
brit milah and we assume that's the day that it's most painful
based on the whole story of Shechem because Shimon and Levi come
in and wipe out the city on the third day.
Straight from רש"י Rashi on the פרשה.
parsha. Yeah I know, that's where the גמרא Gemara got it, straight
from רש"י Rashi on the פרשה. parsha. Okay, so שלישי של מילה
של אברהם היה, shelishi she-milah shel Avraham hayah, ובא הקדוש ברוך הוא
לשאול באברהם u-va Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu lish'ol be-Avraham and God went to
do ביקור חולים bikkur cholim to see how Avraham was doing. הוציא
הקדוש ברוך הוא חמה מנרתיקה כדי שלא להטריח אותו צדיק באורחים. hotzi
Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu chamah mi-ne-tikah kedei she-lo le-atrich oto tzaddik be-orchim.
And God also, you know, made it a very hot day in
order that there would be
no, you know, no... שדרי
ליה אליעזר shadrei leih Eliezer
so אברהם Avraham who of course wanted guests and saw that there
were no guests coming sent אליעזר Eliezer his servant למפק לבר lemafak
lebar to go out of the tent and to go find guests
and bring them in. If they don't come to you you bring
them in. נפק ולא אשכח. Nafak velo ashckach. Out in the heat
of day אליעזר Eliezer went out and couldn't find any guests. אמר
לו מהימנא לך? Amar lo meheimna lach?
So he said to him am I not trusted to you?
הינו דאמרי תם לית הימנותא בעבדי. Hainu deamri tam leit heimanuta beavdei.
You can't trust servants.
No but what I'm not getting exactly is so who is saying
am
I
not trust
oh אברהם Avraham said I don't believe you. Oh I see I
was reading it rhetorically.
I'm sorry I was reading it rhetorically. Okay let's do that again.
Okay so he sent אליעזר. Eliezer. שדרי ליה אליעזר למפק לבר ולא
אשכח. Shadrei leih Eliezer lemafak lebar velo ashckach. אליעזר Eliezer didn't find
them. אמר לו לא מהימנא לך. Amar lo lo meheimna lach. אברהם
Avraham said I don't trust you. You went and you found you
didn't do a good enough job. I'm going to go check myself.
הינו דאמרי תם.
Hainu
deamri tam No kidding. הינו דאמרי תם Hainu deamri tam. לית הימנותא
בעבדי. leit heimanuta beavdei. You can't trust servants. Okay. It's like when
it reminds me when my wife tells me to go find something
and I my my keys or whatever so I looked I couldn't
find them. She says I'm going to go look and then she
finds them in two minutes. Okay.
Yes.
Who was it suggested maybe he was trying to prevent אברהם Avraham
from having to go out?
Oh that's nice. He really didn't look he just was trying he
was complicit with God's plan to protect אברהם Avraham from having to
worry. That's a nice idea.
Okay. לית הימנותא בעבדי. Leit heimanuta beavdei. I don't trust slaves. Okay.
נפק איהו חזייה להקדוש ברוך הוא. Nafak ihu chazyei leHakadosh Baruch Hu.
So אברהם Avraham went out to check for himself whether there was
going to be whether there was going to be
wayfarers and he saw God. דקאי אבבא. Dekayei ababa. That God was
standing there by the gate. הינו דכתיב Hainu dechtiv אל נא תעבור
מעל עבדך. Al na taavor meal avdecha. God
please don't pass by your servant. You've come to visit me please
stay and he was welcoming God who was his guest. His guest
was God. So God please come in. Okay. כיון דחזא דקא אסר
ושרי. Keivan dechaza deka asar veshari. So that's what that's the first
וירא אליו השם באלוני ממרא Vayeira eilav Hashem be'elonei Mamrei and אברהם
Avraham said אל נא תעבור מעל עבדך Al na taavor meal avdecha
because אברהם Avraham basically first sees not the angels but first sort
of like sees God and is asking God to sort of stay.
Okay. Now the angels themselves it's sort of like an interesting like
little bit of shift. Okay. כיון דחזא Keivan dechaza
or God whatever. God saw דקא אסר ושרי deka asar veshari that
he was untying and tying his bandages from the מילה. milah. אמר
לאו אורח ארעא למיקם הכא. Amar lav orach ara lemikam hacha. It's
not appropriate God is apparently saying for me to stay here with
אברהם Avraham revealing himself like this or attending to his wound like
this. הינו דכתיב וישא עיניו וירא והנה שלשה אנשים נצבים עליו. Hainu
dechtiv vayisa einav vayar vehinei shelosha anashim nitzavim alav. He lifted up
his eyes and he saw that there were three people standing over
him. וירא וירץ לקראתם. Vayar vayaratz likratam. And he saw and he
ran to greet them. So what does it mean they were standing
right by him and then he had to run to greet them?
Were they next to him or were they far away? מעיקרא אתו
קמו עליה. Me'ikara atu kamu aleih. Originally they came and stood by
him. כי חזייה דהוה ליה צערא. Ki chazyei dehavah leih tzara. When
they saw that he had pain אמר לאו אורח ארעא למיקם הכא.
Amar lav orach ara lemikam hacha. It's not appropriate for us to
be here so that he's dealing with pain we have to give
him his space. So therefore they stepped back. Okay. Now I don't
really I have to tell you I don't really get how the
גמרא Gemara is weaving this all in because first of all first
it says God came to visit him. What is the visiting of
him before this idea like was that an experience אברהם Avraham had
of God's presence and then there's the idea of scaring away the
guests? Or was the visiting of or keeping away the guests or
was the visiting of him the thing that we say afterwards that
when אברהם Avraham went to the door he saw God's presence? Was
that the visiting of him that the גמרא Gemara was referring to?
And what was that thing of God's presence? Was that the angels
or was that something else? First it sounds like it was just
God being present. But then when it speaks about the angels moving
away and it spoke about God moving away it sounds like God's
visiting of him was manifested through the presence of the angels. So
right it's not exactly clear at least to me and תוספות Tosafot
also deals with it you know about to what degree is this
idea that God came לבקר את החולה levaker et hacholeh sort of
saying that that was manifested through the presence of the angels or
was that something distinct from the angels? So if look if you
look at תוספות Tosafot let's look at תוספות. Tosafot. חזייה להקדוש ברוך
הוא דקאי אבבא. Chazyei leHakadosh Baruch Hu dekayei ababa. תוספות Tosafot says
והינו
דכתיב אל נא תעבור מעל עבדך. veheinau dechtiv al na taavor meal
avdecha. הכא משמע שהשכינה היתה רוצה להסתלק מעל אברהם. Hacha mashma shehaShechina
hayeta rotza lehistalek meal Avraham. The שכינה Shechina wanted to leave. במדרש
משמע שלפי שרצה אברהם לילך לקראת אורחים ולהכניסם אמר להקדוש ברוך הוא
להמתין עד שיכניס אותן. BaMidrash mashma shelefi sheratza Avraham leilech likrat orchim
ulhachnisam amar leHakadosh Baruch Hu lehamtin ad sheyachnis otan. Right so there
he discusses and I think רש"י Rashi says this that God told
אברהם Avraham that אברהם Avraham told God wait here I have to
go welcome the angels and bring in the angels. So that distinguishes
between God's visiting of אברהם Avraham and the angels' visiting of אברהם.
Avraham. Okay but here it sounds a little bit like maybe God's
visiting of אברהם Avraham was the manifested through the visit visiting of
the angels. So a little unclear. Yes, רב דב. Rabbi Dov.
It's a really powerful model, הכנסת אורחים, Hachnasat Orchim, with a kind
of pastoral sensitivity. You go into a room, but then you see
the patient is
just compromised dignity.
I step back. That's a very good point.
Step back here.
Right, it's the people that do ביקור חולים Bikur Cholim and a
שבעה Shiva call or whatever and they're not really clued in to
what the person needs. Right, that's a very good point that
sometimes they say you know, the normal דרשה drasha that they say,
I mean the point that people say is, the מדרש Medrash says
that God came to be מבקר חולים. Mevaker Cholim. Like what did
God do? It doesn't say God did anything. So it just said
well you
know like Woody Allen says ninety-five percent of life is just showing
up, just being there. And that's the ביקור חולים. Bikur Cholim. But
רב דב Rabbi Dov makes an excellent point as well. Sometimes also
you know that the right thing you do, the best way you
do it is when it's time to step back and to leave
or to just not give the person space. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, מאני השלושה אנשים? Mani Hashelosha Anashim? Who are these three people?
מיכאל וגבריאל ורפאל. Michael ve-Gabriel ve-Refael. So these were the three angels.
These three were going to identify them. Of course the naming of
the angels occurs only later in תנ"ך, Tanakh, but then חז"ל Chazal
go and they try to link earlier anonymous angels with specific named
angels. So
מיכאל שבא לבשר שרה, Michael she-ba levasser Sarah, מיכאל Michael came to
inform שרה Sarah of what was going to happen. רפאל, Refael, that's
רפואה, refuah, שבא לרפא את אברהם, she-ba lerapeh et Avraham, to heal
אברהם Avraham from the ברית מילה. brit milah. גבריאל, Gabriel, which is
like גבורה gevurah and power, אזל למהפכי לסדום azal le-hafochi li-Sdom to
overturn סדום. Sdom. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says each one had
a separate job. והכתיב, ve-hakativ, but doesn't the verse say ויבאו שני
המלאכים סדומה בערב, Vayavou shenei hamalakhim Sdoma ba-erev,
the two angels came to סדום Sdom in the evening? So why
do you need two? You only needed one, גבריאל. Gabriel. ואזל מיכאל
בהדי. ve-aza Michael bahadei.
No, מיכאל Michael stayed along לשזביה ללוט leshazvei le-Lot to save לוט.
Lot. So the same way מיכאל, Michael, so it seems like the
linking here is that מיכאל Michael was coming to give good message
to שרה, Sarah, he was the one that was coming to do,
so he came to save לוט. Lot. He was coming to, I
don't know, bring, you know, do good things. דיקנמי דכתיב, diknammi dekhitiv,
I mean why did they pick, you know, מיכאל Michael over רפאל?
Refael? So דיקנמי דכתיב ויהפוך את הערים האל, diknammi dekhitiv Vayahafoch et
hearim ha-el, he turned over those cities. So only one person, only
גבריאל Gabriel actually did the destruction. מיכאל Michael was there to do
the good stuff, to save לוט. Lot. ולא כתיב ויהפכו, velo ketiv
vayahafechu, it doesn't say they turned over.
שמע מינה. shema mina. Now תוספות, Tosafot, look at the תוספות Tosafot
because I think this is also parallels like a רש"י Rashi on
the Torah. תוספות Tosafot says איהו דאזל לשזביה ללוט. ehu de-azal leshazvei
le-Lot. תוספות Tosafot says ותימא, vetema, and you might wonder, דמניין בראשית
רבה deminyan BeReishit Rabbah דאין מלאך אחד עושה שתי שליחויות, de-ein malakh
echad oseh shetei shelichuyot,
one angel can't do two things. So how could מיכאל Michael both
inform אברהם Avraham and save לוט? Lot? ויש לומר, ve-yesh lomar, and
one can say, the גמרא Gemara here doesn't say that by the
way. ויש לומר דכאן לא עשה מיכאל בשליחות אחת ve-yesh lomar de-kan
lo asa Michael bishlichut achat כי מעשה אחד שבישר שרה, ki maaseh
echad she-bisser Sarah, that no,
he did one job, he told שרה, Sarah, then that job was
over, then he got assigned to another job. Okay? שבישר שרה she-bisser
Sarah וכשהלך משם לסדום u-kheshelakh misham le-Sdom אז התחיל שליחות אחרת. az
hitchal shelichut acheret.
So he wasn't doing two things at once, one job finished, he
began the next job. ודוקא בפעם אחת אינו עושה שתי שליחויות. ve-davka
be-paam achat eino oseh shetei shelichuyot. Okay, that's one way to explain
this גמרא. Gemara. But in בראשית רבה BeReishit Rabbah יש שרפאל בא
להוציא את לוט. yesh she-Refael ba lehotzi et Lot.
No, the רפאל Refael who healed אברהם Avraham saved לוט. Lot. And
there it works better. Healing אברהם Avraham and saving לוט. Lot. רפואת
אברהם אינה נזכרת. refuat Avraham eina nizkeret.
First of all he says it doesn't say explicitly in the פסוקים
pesukim that an angel came, that אברהם Avraham was healed. So maybe
that's not an explicit שליחות shelichut so we're allowed to assign him
another one. Number two, ואפילו בא כמו כן לרפא את אברהם ve-afilu
ba kemo khen lerape et Avraham חשיב הכל שליחות אחת chashiv hakol
shelichut achat דרפואה והצלה עניין אחד. de-refua ve-hatzala inyan echad. Healing somebody,
saving somebody, those are connected types of ideas. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot
tries to figure out the proper economy of the angels' jobs. Okay,
back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, גבי אברהם כתיב, gabei Avraham ketiv, ואברהם אמר, ve-Avraham ammar, it
says כן תעשה כאשר דברת. ken taaseh kaasher dibarta.
As soon as אברהם Avraham offered them hospitality they said yes. ומאי
שנא גבי אברהם, u-mai shna gabei Avraham, why,
how is it different, by אברהם Avraham it says כן תעשה כאשר
דברת. ken taaseh kaasher dibarta. ומאי שנא גבי לוט, u-mai shna gabei
Lot, when it came to לוט, Lot, דכתיב ויפצר בם מאד, de-ketiv
vayiftzar bam me'od, he had to pressure them much to accept his
hospitality. דף פ"ז עמוד א. Daf peh zain amud aleph. So אמר
רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar מכאן שמסרבין לקטן ואין מסרבין לגדול. mikan
she-mesarvin le-katan ve-ein mesarvin le-gadol. You see here that you refuse a
small person initially and you don't refuse a big person. Right, it
would be like offensive I guess to somebody who's a חשוב chashuva
person, they extend you an invitation, somebody who's like not so חשוב
chashuva maybe it's offensive for you to be so readily saying yes.
You
know, so that's a certain type of a I don't know דרך
ארץ derech eretz I suppose or a way of reflecting people's different
social status. Okay, כתיב ketiv it says פת לחם pat lechem וכתיב
אל הבקר רץ אברהם. u-khetiv el habakar ratz Avraham. He offers them
bread but he gives them a nice steak. So what's the story?
אמר רבי אלעזר מכאן שצדיקים אומרים מעט ועושים הרבה. amar Rabbi Elazar
mikan she-tzadikim omrim me'at ve-osim harbeh. You see righteous people promise a
little and they do a lot. רשעים reshaim as opposed to the
wicked people אומרים הרבה ואפילו מעט אינם עושים. omrim harbeh ve-afilu me'at
einam osim. They promise a lot and they don't even do a
little. מנלן? minalan? See by עפרון, Efron, וקרי ליה עפרון, Vekari lei
Efron, it's initially it says ארץ ארבע מאות שקל כסף ביני ובינך
מה היא. Eretz arba me'ot shekel kesef beini uveinecha mah hi. Ah,
it's only 400 שקל, Shekel, forget it, nothing, you don't have to
pay anything. Okay,
of course even that, you know, is clearly like dropping a hint,
like it's the way, I mean scholars have said this, that this
was actually that whole exchange by אברם Avram and עפרון Efron was
the classic way that bartering was done, you know, in the Middle
East. You say, "Ach, this thing, it's only worth a hundred dollars.
Yeah, you don't you can have it for free." And you say,
"Right. I wouldn't even tell you..." you know, so that's like it
was the way of bartering back and forth. But anyway, according to
the פשט Pshat of the פסוקים, Psukim, I mean according to what
explicitly he's saying, he's saying I'm not even going to ask you
anything for it. Okay, so so it says so first he promised
to basically give it to him for free. ולבסוף כתיב Ulevasof ketiv
וישמע אברהם אל עפרון. Vayishma Avraham el Efron. אברם Avram heard what
עפרון Efron was really getting at. וישקול אברהם לעפרן את הכסף אשר
דבר באזני בני חת Vayishkol Avraham le'Efron et hakesef asher diber be'oznei
venei Chet ארבע מאות שקל כסף. Arba me'ot shekel kesef. He paid
him the full amount. Okay, not only did he pay him the
full amount, עובר לסוחר. Over lasocher. It was the type of coins
that would be, you know, accepted by any merchant. Although the אחרונים
Acharonim will tell us it's not coins, but it's the type of
metal that was stamped in a way that anybody would accept it
and accept its weight. So the גמרא Gemara says דלא שקל מיניה.
Delo shakal minei. At the end of the day, עפרון Efron only
would refuse to accept from אברם Avram אלא קנטרי Ela kantari except
for a certain type of a large coin
that was, you know, that was acceptable in all types of, you
know, by all merchants but apparently also of greater weight. So it
wasn't only a standard 400 שקל Shekel although שקל Shekel seems to
be a weight, but anyway it was a large 400 שקל. Shekel.
So he promised, he said he would give it for free, and
in the end he demanded a great deal. דאיכא דוכתא דקרו ליה
לתיקלא קנטרי. De'ika duchta dekaru lei letikla kantari. There are places that
call a שקל Shekel a קנטרי. Kantari. So שקל עובר לסוחר Shekel
over lasocher is actually even a bigger coin than a שקל. Shekel.
Okay, כתיב. Ketiv. Back to אברם. Avram. It says קמח Kemach וכתיב
Uchetiv סולת. Soles. He says קמח סולת. Kemach soles. He goes to
שרה Sarah and he says, 'Take קמח Kemach flour, סולת Soles fine
flour.' So the גמרא Gemara asks which is it? Is it coarse
flour or is it fine flour? So rather than reading it as
just an adjective, you know, what type of flour, fine flour, it
reads it as two different things. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רבי יצחק Amar Rabbi Yitzchak מכאן שהאשה צרה עיניה באורחים יותר
מן האיש. Mikan she'ha'ishah tzarah eineha be'orchim yoter min ha'ish. The woman
is a little bit more reluctant to give, you know, the food
to the guests as much as the man is. So he basically
presumably, you know, so it's not exactly clear. So why did אברם
Avram say קמח סולת? Kemach soles? But apparently the way they're reading
it is is that either he said סולת Soles and she only
wanted to give קמח, Kemach, or he said you know don't give
just קמח, Kemach, make sure that it's סולת. Soles. Anyway, it's interesting
why the גמרא Gemara assumes this. You know elsewhere the גמרא Gemara
assumes that you know women are more compassionate or more generous, you
know, besides that it's, you know, drawing like broad generalizations about you
know between the sexes. But anyway maybe women are in the kitchen
and they know how much food that they actually have and have
to feed their family and it's very easy for the man to
just sort of promise a lot. Anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara's interpretation
here.
Okay, כתיב Ketiv לושי ועשי עוגות, Lushi va'asi ugot, knead them and
make cakes. וכתיב ויקח חמאה וחלב ובן הבקר. Uchetiv vayikach chemah vechalav
uven habakar. And then it says he gave them the milk and
the butter and the and the meat. ואילו לחם לא אייתי Ve'ilu
lechem lo ayisi and it never says what happened to the bread.
So לקמייהו? Lekamaihu? אמר אפרים מקשאה Amar Efrayim Maksha'ah תלמידו של רבי
מאיר. Talmido shel Rabbi Meir. Where do we ever have an אפרים
מקשאה? Efrayim Maksha'ah? Right? And then it says the student of רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Why does it ever say somebody is the תלמיד
Talmid of X? Anyway, משמיה דרבי מאיר Mishmei de'Rabbi Meir in the
name of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu אוכל חולין
בטהרה היה. Ochel chullin betaharah hayah. אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu was, you
know, ate even his non-sanctified food only in a state of purity.
It couldn't have come in contact with any טומאה. Tumah. ושרה אמנו
אותו היום פירסה נדה. VeSarah Imenu oto hayom pirsa niddah. And that
day שרה Sarah returned to her youthfulness and she got her period
again after having been a woman of 90. So she became a
נדה. Niddah. So therefore her touching of the bread made the bread
טמא. Tamei.
So that's why he couldn't serve it to that. Okay, I mean
it's fascinating on many levels but anyway one point I'll just bring
out is that okay he ate his חולין בטהרה Chullin betaharah but
why couldn't he give it to them? So that's interesting like you
know that even if they wouldn't have cared, you know, if he
thought that they were Arabs maybe idolaters or whatever, but like what
does it mean that you give them something that you yourself wouldn't
eat right? Even if it's just because of your own personal compunction,
it's not that the food is any worse right? But that's somehow
like you're treating them as less than you. So I think there's
something, you know, interesting because he wouldn't eat it, he didn't feed
it to them.
Yes. אברהם Avraham seems to not have realized that these were actually
angels.
Well, that's part of the whole story, yes. The interesting question is
does he even realize by the end of the story that they're
angels? That's just a פשט Pshat question in the פסוקים. Psukim.
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara suggests it says when he wasn't... he was
standing over them while they were eating... He was eating with them.
Yeah, he didn't want them to feel that they're eating the bread
and he's not eating the bread. That's a good point too. Right,
right, you know part of making them comfortable is that you break
bread with somebody, you don't just serve them. Although it's interesting because
it says והוא עומד עליהם תחת העץ ויאכלו. Vehu omed aleihem tachat
ha'etz vayocheilu. I always assumed the simple sense of the פסוק Pasuk
was he was attending them and they were eating. Right, okay. ויאמרו
אליו, vayomru eilav, they said to him, איה שרה אשתך, aye Sarah
ishtecha, where's Sarah your wife? ויאמר הנה באוהל. vayomer hinei va'ohel. להודיע
ששרה אמנו צנועה הייתה. lehodi'a she-Sarah Imeinu tzenu'ah hayetah. So to tell
you she's in the tent, like she's not out here in public,
you know, she's where women should be in the tent. So this
is obviously an idea of the גמרא Gemara of צניעות tzniut which
is, you know, that women are private and not out in the
public. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב ואיתימא רב יצחק יודעים היו מלאכי
השרת ששרה אמנו באוהל הייתה. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav v'iteima Rav
Yitzchak yodi'im hayu malachei hashareit she-Sarah Imeinu ba'ohel hayetah. Obviously they knew,
so why did they ask him? Like why? But אלא, ella, now,
איו באוהל, ayo ba'ohel, כדי לחבבה על בעלה, kedei lechabevah al ba'alah,
in order to make her dear to her husband, so her husband
should realize oh she's so צניעות, tzniut, she's in the tent. So
you want to, I mean that's the way רש"י Rashi does it,
right? I mean you wouldn't have to, you didn't have to explicitly
connect it to the previous thing, that what made her dear to
her husband was that he remembered how צניעות tzniut she was. It
could have just been that by asking after somebody's husband or somebody's
wife, you know, it brings up warm feelings. But that's why they
did it. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא אמר כדי לשגר לה כוס של
ברכה. Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Chanina amar kedei leshadger lah kos shel berachah.
No, no, no. It was because they actually wanted to, and this
actually I think is a nicer read, they wanted to somehow incorporate
her in what they were doing. And I think that that's closer
to the פשט, pshat, right? ויאמר הנה באוהל. vayomer hinei va'ohel. ויאמר
שוב אשוב אליך כעת חיה והנה בן לשרה אשתך. Vayomer shuv ashuv
eilecha ke-eis chayyah vehinei ben le-Sarah ishtecha. They're about to tell him
something that's going to happen to Sarah his wife, right? So right,
admittedly she was in the tent, right? Obviously clearly in that society
it would be inappropriate for the woman to be out there, right,
attending to these male guests and so on, right? But the point
is to just tell the husband something that applies to the wife.
How do you, you know, how do you make the wife more
of a subject in that, you know, less of somebody that's just
talked about? You know, it's actually something that relates to her. So
by sort of at least in his mind bringing her into the
conversation, where is Sarah? Like this is a message that is directed
not, you know, to Sarah as well. She's not here but the
message is directed to Sarah, it's not just directed to you. So
I think that by saying that the, to send her the כוס
של ברכה, kos shel berachah, right, you בענטש bentsh and after you
בענטש bentsh you send her the cup that she drinks from it,
that's the way that even if she's not in the room she's
part of the proceedings. You recognize her presence, you recognize her participation
even when she's not in the room. So I think that that's
a very powerful read and probably like the פשט pshat of the
פסוקים psukim of why they're bringing up Sarah. Okay, so כדי לשגר
כוס של ברכה. kedei leshadger kos shel berachah. תני משום רבי יוסי
למה נקוד על איו שבאליו? Tani mishum Rabbi Yosei lama nakud al
ayo she-be-eilav? ויאמרו אליו איה שרה אשתך. Vayomru eilav aye Sarah ishtecha.
Why does it have the dots over the אלף, alef, you know,
the יוד yud and the ואו? vav? What are those dots signify?
Because that's how it's written in the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. So
למדה תורה דרך ארץ. limdah Torah derech eretz. The Torah is teaching
you a proper practice, courtesy, שישאל אדם באכסניא שלו, she-yish'al adam b'achsanya
shelo, that you should ask after
your hostess, you know, you're being hosted by somebody, you ask the
host about the hostess. Now where does she get that from the
dots over the word אליו? eilav? So רש"י Rashi just says well
cause the dots are extra so therefore you know it's just signaling
to you that you should know that this is a general practice.
Okay. So what does that have to do with specifically those letters?
So תוספות Tosafot actually says no, actually the גמרא Gemara means the
flip. איה, aye, where is Sarah ishtecha, and the dots are over
the אלף, alef, יוד, yud, and ואו. vav. If you just read
those letters what does that spell? איו. ayo. Which is איה aye
in the masculine. So really it's saying the same way when you're
dealing with the host you say how's your wife doing, then when
you're dealing with the hostess you say how's your husband doing? So
it's actually not about, you know, it's actually telling you the gender
equality here. Okay so that's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. That,
so the גמרא Gemara says, והאמר שמואל. v'ha-amar Shmuel. Now how can
you say that when you're dealing with a host you should ask
after his wife? Doesn't שמואל Shmuel say אין שואלין בשלום אשה כלל?
ein sho'alin b'shlom isha klal? That you don't ask after the welfare
of somebody's wife because you know maybe it leads to
inappropriate interactions. So what are you doing so interested in my wife?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so אין שואלין באשה כלל. ein sho'alin
b'isha klal. So על ידי בעלה שאני. al yedei ba'alah shani. No,
no, no. If you can ask her husband, right, then it wouldn't
be inappropriate, right? Because nobody is going to try to, you know,
sort of arrange some assignation or whatever, you know, through the husband.
So therefore if you can ask the husband how's your wife doing?
Please send your wife my best. I don't know, you could ask
your wife, that would also be a little funny. Anyway, fine. You
don't ask the woman her, so might be and you're not supposed
to even ask the woman herself. Okay,
because you know you ask her hey how've you been, how you
doing, whatever, then you know that's like then you start having too
many interactions with women which is dangerous.
Yes. But the פשט pshat is, in other words in traditional Bedouin
tents, the wives have their own tent. They don't eat together. The
husbands and wives don't eat together. The men and women are completely
separate.
The women eat separately from the men.
Right, right, right. Yeah I mean clearly that society that was sort
of the צניעות tzniut of that society, right? So absolutely.
Yeah and it makes it even more.
Look, when the חרדי Chareidi פוסקים poskim deal with the issue of
שבע ברכות, sheva brachot, a regular question comes up: are you allowed
to say שבע ברכות sheva brachot if the כלה kallah isn't in
the room? Because the כלה kallah is off in her room with
her women friends, and the groom is in his room with his
friends. Here they are, they just married, they're celebrating the marriage, but
the men and the women are in two totally separate spaces. So
can you say שבע ברכות sheva brachot with the groom without there
being the כלה kallah present? So clearly, you know, that was anyway.
But I do think the idea to center the כוס של ברכה
kos shel bracha is a powerful way of saying how do we
include her, how do we include her even if she's not here?
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this, last of the narrow lines.
אחרי בלתי היתה לי עדנה, Acharei b'losi haysa li ednah,
after I was worn away, I you know, after my old age,
I had youth. ואדני זקן. V'adoni zaken.
And the end of you know. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda,
אחר שנתבלה הבשר רבו הקמטים, acher she-nisbalah habasar raba ha-kmatim,
after the flesh had been like worn away and the wrinkles had
increased, נתעדנה הבשר, nisadnah habasar, now the flesh had become youthful, you
know like supple, ונתפשטו הקמטים v'nispashhtu ha-kmatim
and the wrinkles had flattened out. So that's what אחרי בלתי היתה
לי עדנה acharei b'losi haysa li ednah means. וחזר היופי למקומו, V'chazar
hayofi limkomo, and the beauty returned to its place. So I just
thought this was funny, רש"י Rashi says that the French word for
קמטים, kmatim, רש"י Rashi says was prut-sant or whatever that is, but
anyway to me it looked like the word prunes, just thought I'd
mention that anyway.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay. כתיב, Ksiv, it says
ואדני זקן. v'adoni zaken. Now when Sarah's saying "How can I, after
I've grown old, you know, have youth?" By the way, the funny
thing here is that Sarah's sort of saying it as a rhetorical
statement, and the גמרא Gemara is reading it literally. אחרי בלתי היתה
לי עדנה, Acharei b'losi haysa li ednah, after I've grown old I
should have youth? ואדני זקן, V'adoni zaken, and my master is old,
right?
So the גמרא Gemara reads it as "Look, this just happened, I
just became young." That's the גמרא. Gemara. She became a נדה, niddah,
she got her period back, right? So actually she's describing a miracle
that's just occurred. But the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is
she's saying like "Should this, should I be able to become youthful
again? And also my master is old." ואדני זקן, V'adoni zaken, Avraham
is old. וכתיב, V'ksiv, ואני זקנתי. v'ani zakanti. Now when God tells
it over to Avraham, he says "למה זה צחקה שרה לאמר האף
אמנם אלד ואני זקנתי?" Lama zeh tzachakah Sarah lemor, haaf omnam eleid
vaani zakanti?
Sarah said "How could I have birth and I've grown old?" And
God did not say what Sarah said, but she said "How could
I have birth and Avraham is old?" Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says דלא מותיב הקדוש ברוך הוא כדקאמרה איהי. d'lo mo-siv HaKadosh Baruch
Hu k'dikamra eehi.
God did not say back to Avraham what Sarah had said. So
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, we taught in the
house of Rabbi Yishmael, גדול שלום, gadol shalom, great is peace, like
in שלום בית, shalom bayis, you know between husband and wife, שאפילו
הקדוש ברוך הוא שינה בו. she'afilu HaKadosh Baruch Hu shina bo. Even
God changed, you know,
the statement in order not to create marital discord. שנאמר ותצחק שרה
בקרבה לאמר, Shene'emar v'titzchak Sarah b'kirbah lemor, Sarah said "And how could
my master be old? ואדני זקן." V'adoni zaken. וכתיב V'ksiv and when
God told it over it says, ויאמר ה' אל אברהם, Vayomer Hashem
el Avraham, why did Sarah laugh saying ואני זקנתי, vaani zakanti, I
am old. Now the interesting issue is that I think it's the
חתם סופר Chatam Sofer or one of the פוסקים poskim say that
this does not mean an outright lie, God actually it was a
selective truth because Sarah actually did say that she was old, I
mean not with those words, but she said after I have you
know been worn away how can I have youth? So Sarah basically
was saying "I'm old and Avraham is old." And what God told
it over,
he only told over half of it, that she said that she
was old. Now I don't know if that's
פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, not פשט pshat of the גמרא,
Gemara, because the גמרא Gemara actually is having Sarah not say she's
old, it's having Sarah say that she just became youthful,
right? Not that she's being rhetorical and astound and wondering, but she
actually is declaring that she became youthful. So according to the גמרא,
Gemara, God really did say the complete opposite or whatever, but did
not say a partial truth, actually said something different than what Sarah
said. Okay, anyway the גמרא Gemara says like this, back to now
she gave birth and we're jumping fast forwarding a little bit, and
it's the party when יצחק Yitzchak is weaned. ותאמר מי מלל לאברהם,
Vatomer mi milel l'Avraham, who has spoken to Avraham, היניקה בנים שרה,
heynika banim Sarah,
that Sarah would you know would
nurse children. So the גמרא Gemara says כמה בנים היניקה שרה? kama
banim heynika Sarah? What do you mean בנים? banim? How many children
did she nurse? She only nursed one child. So why is it
in the plural? אמר רבי לוי, Amar Rabbi Levi, אותו היום שגמל
אברהם את יצחק בנו, oso hayom shegemal Avraham es Yitzchak bno, that
day that Avraham weaned יצחק Yitzchak his son, עשה סעודה גדולה, asa
seuda gedola, he made a big feast. היו כל אומות העולם מרננים
ואומרים, Hayu kol umos haolam meranenim v'omrim, and everybody was mocking, you
know, and saying, ואומרים ראיתם זקן וזקנה שהביאו אסופי מן השוק, v'omrim
re'isun zakin v'zekeina she-heiviu asufi min hashuk,
did you see this elderly couple, they brought this foundling from the
marketplace, they found this orphan, ואומרים בננו הוא, v'omrim baneinu hu, and
they're claiming it's their son. 100 years old and 90 years old
they gave birth, what a joke, it's all a fake. ולא עוד
אלא שעושים משתה גדול לאמת דבריהם, v'lo od ela she-osim mishteh gedol
l'amet divreihem, and they're making a big feast in order to make
people believe that this is true, you know, everybody will now talk
about the feast and the weaning whatever, it's all a farce. מה
עשה אברהם אבינו? Ma asa Avraham Avinu? What did אברהם Avraham do?
So הלך וזימן כל גדולי הדור... halach v'zimin kol gedolei hador... וזימן
נשותיהם, v’ziman n’shoteihem,
so he made sure that all of the—see, the idea of a
גדול הדור gadol hador is already in the גמרא, Gemara, except it
happens to be a non-Jew at that time. He invited all of
the great people of the—of that generation, and Sarah all of their
wives, so that everybody should be present and see. וכל אחת ואחת
הביאה בנה עמה, v’chol achat v’achat hevia b’nah imah, and everybody brought
their children with them, their, you know, their infants with them. ומיניקותיהן
לא הביאו, u’menikoteihen lo heviu, they did not bring the nursemaids. ונעשה
נס בשרה אמנו, v’na’asa nes b’Sarah Imeinu,
and a miracle happened with Sarah and ונפתחו דדיה כשני מעיינות, v’nift’chu
dadeha k’shnei ma’ayanot, and her breasts opened up like two wellsprings, והניקה
כולם, v’henika kulam, and she was able to nurse all of them.
So that's הניקה בנים. henika banim. So everybody saw that, you know,
you don't give—you can't nurse unless you've given birth, that it really
was her child. Okay, so now, of course, skeptics are never—rivers.
Right, right, exactly. So now, of course, you know, skeptics are never,
you know, satisfied. ועדיין היו מרננים ואומרים, v’adayin hayu m’ran’nim v’omrim, and
they would still be like, you know, gossiping and mocking and saying:
אם שרה הבת
תשעים שנה תלד, im Sarah habat tishim shana teled, maybe Sarah who
is 90—echoing the פסוק pasuk here—90 years old could give birth, ואברהם
בן מאה שנה יוליד, v’Avraham ben mea shana yolid,
but could Abraham have sired children? So maybe there's clear evidence that
Sarah's the mother, but who knows if Abraham is the father? Of
course, the irony here is that I think a man can actually
can sire children even, you know, at the age of 100 or
whatever, the semen is still, you know, potent. But anyway, but that's
what they were saying. Who said it was Abraham? Okay, so מיד,
miyad, immediately
נהפך קלסתר
פניו של יצחק, nehpach klastar panav shel Yitzchak, so Isaac's visage immediately
changed, transformed, ונדמה לאברהם, v’nidmeh l’Avraham, and immediately and he looked like
Abraham. Of course, it's pretty funny, so for the first—so for the
first years of his infancy, he looked different, but then all of
a sudden his face changed.
Anyway, that is what happened, that's exactly what happened. Oh, really?
Absolutely. In terms of like, babies look
like—babies look like change. Oh, like,
you know, they're like, "oh, looks like you, looks like you."
But then eventually it matures. Okay, interesting. Okay, right, which is fine,
which
means that everything in this midrash happened exactly...
okay, right. Okay, so then after he went out of the baby
stage, his face when it—so fine, let's say it this way, when
his facial features sort of clarified, it became clear he looked just
like Abraham. So they could tell that he was Abraham's son. Okay,
ונדמה לאברהם, v’nidmeh l’Avraham, פתחו כולם ואמרו, pitchu kulam v’amru, then
everybody conceded and said: אברהם הוליד את יצחק, Avraham holid et Yitzchak,
right, which is the beginning of the פרשה parsha of תולדות. Toldot.
אלה תולדות יצחק בן אברהם אברהם הוליד את יצחק, Eleh toldot Yitzchak
ben Avraham Avraham holid et Yitzchak, everybody admitted Abraham sired Isaac. Now
the גמרא Gemara has one like a different shifting gears a little
bit. עד אברהם לא היה זקנה, ad Avraham lo haya zikna, but
until Abraham's time there was no old age. People died, but they
didn't go through a period where their age was reflected in their
body, okay, which is very strange because you just have the whole
story about Abraham and Sarah wondering if they can give birth and
clearly it seems like Sarah's body was different, אחרי בלותי הייתה לי
עדנה. acharei v’loti hayta li edna. So maybe men weren't, I don't
know, so let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara describes this.
מאן דהוה בעי למשתעי בהדי אברהם, man d’hava ba’i l’mishta’ei bahadi Avraham,
if somebody wanted to talk to Abraham, משתעי בהדי יצחק, mishta’ei bahadi
Yitzchak, would accidentally be talking to Isaac because now we say that
Isaac looked like Abraham and there was no difference in age, age
wasn't reflected on their body. So Abraham looked just like Isaac even
as adults, so people would be talking to the wrong person. Okay,
בהדי יצחק, bahadi Yitzchak, if you wanted to talk to Isaac, משתעי
בהדי אברהם, mishta’ei bahadi Avraham, you'd wind up talking to Abraham. So
and this was a real problem, you couldn't tell the son from
the father. So אתא אברהם בעי רחמי, ata Avraham ba’ei rachamei, Abraham
came prayed that the old age should be reflected on him, והוה
זקנה, v’hava zikna, and there was old age, שנאמר ואברהם זקן בא
בימים. shene’emar v’Avraham zaken ba bayamim. So and the point is that
this is the first time in the תורה Torah that it says
that somebody was old.
Okay, so it's interesting, right? I mean, cause the פסוקים psukim earlier
do reflect the fact, obviously old age would change your ability to
have children, right? אדוני זקן, adoni zaken, I mean, it's interesting the
גמרא Gemara didn't even quote that. Before it says אברהם זקן בא
בימים, Avraham zaken ba bayamim, which is, you know, when he goes
to look for a wife for Isaac. Earlier it said ואדוני זקן.
v’adoni zaken. So clearly it's—so I don't even know how they make
that work, right? He's saying אדוני זקן adoni zaken and according to
this Abraham only wanted זקנה zikna after Isaac was born and started
looking like him. But besides which, the גמרא Gemara could accept the
idea that after a certain age, you know, you're harder to have
children, that's clearly in the whole narrative of Abraham and Sarah, but
it's saying that it wasn't reflected on the body. But again, by
Sarah, it was reflected on the body, she says בלותי b’loti and
the גמרא Gemara even emphasizes that.
So I get that this little concern about the origin of old
age is said in that hermeneutic context. Right, but it's a very
powerful mythic explanation, but it links aging with identity.
Like Abraham—the רחמים rachamim was Abraham was losing his identity, people didn't
know who he was. There's some link
here between the way you change over time
as you age and your uniqueness.
Right. Right.
Right, and that's felt like— Right, I mean I agree with that.
I mean it does have to do because it specifically puts it
in the context that יצחק Yitzchak looked just like him, but I
would sort of reframe it as, you know, do you want to
look, I mean some people do, but like the גמרא Gemara is
saying
אברהם Avraham did not want to look when he was eighty like
he looked when he was forty. He wants, you know, his life
experience and his age or whatever to be reflected in how he
looks.
Right, that's counter-cultural to contemporary.
Right, everybody wants to look young. Right, exactly. And it's also especially
if you believe that a society in which honors, right, and reveres
older age, right, so then clearly you want that reflected. But even
without the question about receiving honor, but just like, you know, you
don't want to look anymore like a ten year old or a
twenty year old, right? You know, you've gone through a lot in
life and you may, if you own that, then you want that
sort of reflected. So anyway, exactly. So, okay, עד יעקב, Ad Yaakov,
now here's another story, עד יעקב לא הוה חולשא, Ad Yaakov lo
hava chulsha, until יעקב Yaakov there was no real sickness.
Because it doesn't say people got sick before that. אתא יעקב בעא
רחמי והוה חולשא, Ata Yaakov ba’ei rachamei vehava chulsha, יעקב Yaakov prayed
and there was sickness leading to death. שנאמר ויאמר ליוסף הנה אביך
חלה, Shenemar vayomer l’Yosef hinei avicha choleh, that's the first time it
says that somebody was sick. Okay, now, now why does somebody want
sickness? So again, this is sickness leading to, we could say sickness
in general puts you in touch with the fragility of life, you
know, makes you more sensitive, more vulnerable, etc. But here I think
it's specifically about also leading to death because you know it's preparing
for your death. If there's an illness leading up to death, you're
able to prepare mentally, put your affairs in order, and so on.
Okay, you know, the challenge nowadays is that the dying process is
so prolonged, right, so that raises other challenges. עד אתא אלישע לא
הוה דחלש ואתפח, Ad ata Elisha lo hava dechalash ve-itpach, until אלישע
Elisha came, nobody got sick and got better. All you had was
the sickness leading to death. אתא אלישע בעא רחמי ואתפח. Ata Elisha
ba’ei rachamei ve-itpach. Now אלישע Elisha prayed that he should be healed
from his sickness. So then it was introduced the idea that the
sickness doesn't always lead to death. שנאמר ואלישע חלה את חליו אשר
ימות בו. Shenemar ve-Elisha chala et chalyo asher yamut bo. He had
the sickness that he would die by it, מכלל דחלי חלי אחריני,
michlal dechali chali achrinei, which indicates
that he had become sick other times. And until that point it
never said somebody got sick and got better. Only by אלישע Elisha
do you see implicitly that he had been sick before and got
better. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, which also creates this
powerful whole תשובה teshuva model, right? If you associate sickness with death
and then you're sick but you know that you can maybe pray
and get better, right, then that's, the whole thing becomes very much
about doing תשובה teshuva and praying and so on, it creates this
whole other dynamic. Right, what to do about the fact that you
just get head colds and when that happens? Like, I don't know
if the גמרא Gemara is referring at all to that type of
sickness. גמרא Gemara might be referring only to like serious illness, you
know. Okay, so תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, שלשה חלאים
חלה אלישע, shlosha cholayim chala Elisha,
אלישע Elisha had three sicknesses. אחד שדחפו לגיחזי בשתי ידיו, echad shedachfo
l’Gechazi bishtei yadav, one he got for pushing away גיחזי Gechazi with
two hands. You know, גיחזי Gechazi acted inappropriately, he called back the
whatever, whoever, נעמן, Naaman, who was the guy? Anyway, to get all
the gifts. Anyway, and אלישע Elisha pushed him back, you know, not
push him with the left and draw him close with the right,
but you know totally rejected him. ואחד שגירה דובים בתינוקות, ve-echad shegeira
dubim bitinokot, and one you might remember the little, the kids were
mocking him and he sent...
How many? Forty-two.
Yeah, and he sent the bears after them. ואחד, ve-echad, I'm very,
I'm very happy so far in the last two דפים dappim we've
had my name come up twice. We had the bear of fire,
you might remember the
distraction, anyway, fine. ואחד שמת בו, ve-echad shemet bo, yeah, I don't
necessarily do good things here, I don't know. Anyway, one that brought
about his death, שנאמר ואלישע חלה את חליו אשר ימות בו. shenemar
ve-Elisha chala et chalyo asher yamut bo. Okay, finally, shifting gears from
the אגדתא. Aggadata. Okay, אלא עד שלא יתחילו במלאכה צא ואמור להם
על מנת שאין לכם אלא פת וקטנית בלבד. ella ad shelo yatchilu
bamlacha tze ve-emor lahem al menat she-ein lachem ela pat vekitnit bilvad.
So this is the father saying before they start and then we'll
have to give them huge feasts, tell them no, no, no, I'm
only going to feed you bread and some legumes. אמר ליה רב
אחא בריה דרב יוסף לאפחוזי פת קטנית תנן או פת וקטנית תנן.
amar lei Rav Acha brei deRav Yosef l’afchuzei pat kitnit tnan o
pat vekitnit tnan. Do we mean a bread made out of legumes,
like rice bread or something, or
do we mean bread and legumes? אמר ליה האלוהים צריכה ו. amar
lei HaElohim tzericha vav. No, no, it needs the ו, vav, פת
וקטנית, pat vekitnit, that's what he was sort of and that's what
he was agreeing. כי מורידא דלברואת, ki morida diLivrot, like you need
a, רש״י Rashi says the מורידא morida is like this big stick
that you would use on a boat to keep away from the
shore and like when you're going down this river, there was a
river called לברואת. Livrot. So anyway, you would need that stick to
keep away from the shore. I guess like a ו vav is
like a stick. So you need to separate I guess the words
of פת pat and קטנית kitnit like you need this stick to
keep the boat away from the shore.
No, לברואת Livrot is the name of the river, like you need
that stick when you're going in the river. I think is what
רש״י Rashi says.
רבא חובל מנהיג בו את
הספינה.
Rava chovel manhig bo et
hasfina. Yeah.
Oh no, I got it reversed. מורידא Morida is the name of
the river... I— And
and the לברוות, livrot, wait a minute, שמא נהרא
מורידא.
shema nahara
Morida.
מורדייא עץ. Mordaya etz.
No, I was right the first time. Right. מורידא Morida is שמא
נהרא shema nahara and the מורידא, Morida, right right right right. The
לברוות livrot is the name of the river and the מורידא Morida
is the stick that keeps you in the middle that keeps in
the middle of the river. Okay, רבן גמליאל אומר אינו צריך הכל
כמנהג המדינה. Rabban Gamliel omer eno tsarikh ha-kol k-minhag ha-medinah.
Even if you stipulate with them to feed them, you're not, you
don't give them more than the standard. Okay, הכל לפי מה? ha-kol
l-fi mah? When it says everything goes by the standard, what do
you mean by everything? I say תנן, tnan, השוכר את הפועל ואמר
לו כאחד וכשניים מבני העיר. hasokher et ha-poel v-amar lo k-echad o
kishnayim mibnei ha-ir. You hire a worker and you say what's your
pay gonna be? Yeah, what the normal workers get paid. Okay, like
a normal person in the city would get paid for the job.
So what does that mean? Let's say there's a range. נותן לו
כפחות שבשכירות דברי רבי יהושע. noten lo kapachot she-bi-skirut divrei Rabbi Yehoshua.
You give him the bottom end of the scale. וחכמים אומרים משמנין
ביניהם. v-chakhamim omrim mshamnin beineihem. No,
no, no, you give him the median of the scale, the average
of the scale, not the bottom. So what does it say הכל
כמנהג המדינה? ha-kol k-minhag ha-medinah? Which one of those is the מנהג
המדינה? minhag ha-medinah? You know, so the גמרא Gemara assumes that the
מנהג minhag means to push you not to say to give the
very bottom is not the מנהג, minhag, the מנהג minhag would mean
some type of an average, you know, if you want to be
the standard, the standard doesn't mean the minimum. So if there's a
range, the standard is in the middle. Alright, so now we go
on. Yes. Please, yes.
Like what happened?
Why all the אגדתא? aggadeta? Well, there was a good, it was,
I mean, certainly we introduced the idea of the סעודה seudah of
אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak v-Yaakov. Now we didn't really, we just
said their children of אברהם יצחק Avraham Yitzchak they deserve a big
סעודה. seudah. It wasn't linked to the סעודה seudah of אברהם, Avraham,
but the גמרא Gemara did link it that way and that gave
him... the גמרא Gemara sometimes uses an opening. I mean, obviously there
were these aggadic traditions, right? Some of them are short in בראשית
רבה. Bereishit Rabbah. You know that there were these traditions because they
appear often in parallel in the בבלי Bavli and the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
right? So the גמרא Gemara sometimes like, you know, sometimes it brings
in אגדתא aggadeta to deepen and elaborate a halakhic discussion. Sometimes if
you give it a little opening, it'll say oh, well we need
to find where we're going to talk about all the אגדתא aggadeta
about אברהם. Avraham. Here's a perfect place, you know, so that's why
they do it, you know.
No, it goes off the fact that ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, רבי
יוחנן... Rabbi Yochanan...
Right, so that is true. Sometimes the גמרא Gemara does decide like
we're going to like now spend some time on אגדתא aggadeta and
there were multiple openings, right? What was the opening before that got
us into the whole stuff about רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש?
Resh Lakish? I'm thinking about it. You have to go back to
83a.
Yeah, I don't even remember how we initially got there.
Yeah, let's see. Right, at the
top of 83a, you've got רב יוסף מאי דכתיב תשת חשך ויהי
לילה. Rav Yosef mai dikhtiv tashet choshekh v-vi laila. How'd we get
to that? In other words, there's a link.
Yeah, somehow. I mean, it's so much through like one thing leading
to another thing, right? But partly it's so but partly it's just
that it had an opportunity to do it and it is true,
sometimes it wants to say like this is going to be a
big aggadic section like you have that in גיטין, Gittin, you have
that elsewhere. Okay, what I actually find interesting is whether, you know,
the that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi sometimes links it's always by like this
like sometimes tenuous link and sometimes the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has it in
exactly the same place as the בבלי, Bavli, not always, which also
shows that there was like this is where we discuss this אגדתא,
aggadeta, you know, it's type of a tradition. Right.
So that's where I'm like these things don't seem like the link
between these and בבא מציעא Bava Metzia doesn't seem very...
Right, so I don't think... Right, so it's really nice when the
אגדתא aggadeta is there to be a reflection on some of the
halakhic themes, right? And then that's very rich sort of the way
those interact. But I think we have to accept that sometimes maybe
you could read it this way, you know, find a way to
make the link, but I do think sometimes it's just like they
had אגדתא aggadeta they wanted to tell, you know, where are you
going to tell it? Okay, משנה ואלו אוכלין מן התורה. Mishnah: V-elu
okhlin min ha-Torah. The follow... now we shift because we are going
back to the idea of like workers' rights, you know, I mean
it wasn't all about workers' rights, there was different things about like
what are the terms of the stipulations and so on, but obviously
that's the broader theme, like what are the terms and therefore what
are the things are there to protect workers or to, you know...
and therefore and so here we turn to actually a מצוה mitzvah
in the תורה, Torah, which is when you have somebody working for
you, they're allowed to eat, right? The תורה Torah says it: כי
תבא בכרם רעך, ki tavo b-kerem re'ekha, you go into your friend's
vineyard, ואכלת ענבים כנפשך שבעך, v-akhalta anavim k-nafshekha save'kha,
you can eat, you know, the grapes to satisfy yourself, ואל כליך
לא תתן, v-el kelyekha lo titten, but don't store it up in
your thing, but as you're going through, you can eat grapes and
there's no limit. Now, the פסוקים pesukim there don't say that you
are working. According to the simple sense of the פסוקים pesukim you
could say I could just walk into your vineyard and start eating
grapes, right? I'm crossing through your vineyard to get from one place
to the other. I mean, that's a big problem. Just 'cause I'm
cutting through your yard, first of all, who let me cut through
your yard? Right, trespassing! And oh, I'm cutting through your yard and
here's some grapes, I'm gonna eat some grapes. Like, we would call
that, you know, theft, right? But so the גמרא, Gemara, like and
we'll see how it does it in the פסוקים, pesukim, understands that
no, we're not talking about somebody just cutting through the yard. We're
talking about you're working for the person. And then it's sort of
like the הלכה halakhah of לא תחסום שור בדישו. lo takhsom shor
b-disho. You know, as a cow is threshing, you can't muzzle it.
Like, what does it mean to be working for someone and having
all this food around you and not being able to actually, you
know, take some of it? So it allows a worker... As he's
working to nibble on the food, or actually not even nibble, you
can fill yourself up, but you can't store it away. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara now tries to identify what are the parameters when
a worker is allowed to be doing this. Yes.
Just a side point, so according to the Talmud and the הלכה,
halacha, I can't walk through your field, but can I walk through...
Well the גמרא Gemara discussed that earlier in בבא קמא Bava Kamma
that יהושע Yehoshua was מנחיל את הארץ manchil et ha'aretz on certain
תנאים tenaim to allow it under certain circumstances, but not in others.
The general rule is no, there's certain exceptions to it, yes.
And בשמיטה biShemita your field isn't yours.
Well that's true. Let's look at
the משנה. Mishna. ואלו אוכלים מן התורה: Ve'eilu ochlim min haTorah: The
following workers are entitled to eat the food that they're working with:
עושה במחובר לקרקע, oseh bemechubar lekarka, if you're dealing with stuff that's
still growing from the ground, that's connected to the ground, בשעת גמר
מלאכה, bish'at gmar melacha, and you're dealing with it during the final
period, basically you're picking the apples, you're harvesting the grapes. If you're
just weeding or watering or whatever, the stuff is still growing, you
can't. But if you're in the process of finishing it, picking it
out of the ground, then you can actually take some for yourself.
If I'm harvesting the apples I can eat those apples?
Exactly. Okay. ובתלוש מן הקרקע. Uvetalush min hakarka. Now let's say you're
dealing with stuff that's already been taken off of the ground, you're
dealing with stomping on the grapes, okay? So עד שלא נגמרה מלאכתו.
ad shelo nigmra melachto. You can do it until the מלאכה melacha
is not complete. Now here the word of מלאכה melacha complete means
something else. Before the מלאכה melacha complete meant until the time when
you are actually doing the harvest. Here you do it until it's
done and until it's done is going to have a הלכתי halachic
meaning, like until it's fit for תרומות ומעשרות, trumot uma'asrot, but we'll
see what that means. But
the point to remember is that it's basically a mirror image. When
it's connected to the ground, you're only entitled to do it when
it is the final labor of taking it from the ground. When
it's not connected to the ground after it's been harvested, you're only
entitled to do it before the end of the process. Okay? So
just remember that they're mirror images. Okay. ובדבר שגידולו מן הארץ. Uvidvar
shegidulo min ha'aretz. And when it's not connected to the ground, at
least it has to have come from the ground. ואלו שאין אוכלים,
Ve'eilu she'ein ochlim, the following can't eat, so this is just going
to be the reverse. העושה במחובר לקרקע, Ha'oseh bemechubar lekarka,
if you're dealing with stuff connected to the ground בשעה שאין גמר
מלאכה, besha'ah she'ein gmar melacha, if it's prior to the end of
the stage, ובתלוש מן הקרקע, uvetalush min hakarka, if it's been harvested,
מאחר שנגמרה מלאכתו, me'achar shenigmra melachto, after the basic work has basically
been done. Okay? ובדבר שאין גידולו מן הארץ, Uvidvar she'ein gidulo min
ha'aretz, and if it's something that doesn't grow from the ground you're
also not allowed to eat. Let's start the גמרא Gemara about where
this comes from. מנא הני מילי? Mena hanei milei? What's the source
of this? דכתיב: Dechtiv: כי תבא בכרם רעך, Ki tavo bekerem re'echa,
if you go into your
friend's vineyard, ואכלת, ve'achalta, you shall eat. אשכחן כרם, Ashkechan kerem, we
know it's a vineyard, כל מילי מנלן? kol milei minalan? How do
I know other things other than a vineyard? גמרינן מכרם. Gamrinan mikarem.
No, כרם kerem is a paradigm. מה כרם מיוחד דבר שגידולו קרקע
ובשעת גמר מלאכה פועל אוכל בו, Mah kerem meyuchad davar shegidulo karka
uvish'at gmar melacha po'el ochel bo, כרם kerem has the following features:
it grows from the ground, it is the period of ending of
the labor, the harvest, and a worker can eat. We don't know
yet it's a worker, but we'll show that. אף כל דבר שגידולו
מן הקרקע ובשעת גמר מלאכה פועל אוכל בו, Af kol davar shegidulo
min hakarka uvish'at gmar melacha po'el ochel bo, we'll just extrapolate, anything
like that. No, the גמרא Gemara says maybe it's only a vineyard.
מה לכרם שכן חייב בעוללות? Mah lekerem shekein chayav be'olelot?
כרם kerem has a special gift that's given to the poor, the
עוללות, olelot, the unfinished grapes. So maybe it has your special entitlements
for workers, maybe it doesn't apply to other types of produce. No,
גמרינן מקמה. gamrinan mikamah. There's another source, because the גמרא Gemara speaks
about when you're harvesting wheat. קמה גופה מנלן? Kamah gufah minalan? דכתיב:
Dechtiv: כי תבא בקמת רעך, Ki tavo beqamat re'echa, when you come
into your friend's standing wheat, וקטפת מלילות בידך, vekataphta melilot beyadecha, and
you can take with your hand, some of the kernels. ואל חרמש
לא תניף על קמת רעך, Ve'el chermesh lo tanif al kamat re'echa,
you can't go with your sickle and start harvesting for yourself some
of the wheat. You can pick some of the kernels with your
hand. So therefore it applies to a vineyard and it applies to
wheat, so it applies to everything. Source says one minute. מה לקמה
שכן חייבת בחלה? Mah lekamah shekein chayavat bechallah? Maybe only wheat because
wheat has a special thing, you give חלה, challah, so maybe also
give this thing to the workers. ומי אמר דהאי קמה קמה דמחייבת
בחלה היא? Umi amar dehai kamah kamah demichayevet bechallah hi? How do
you know we're talking about grain and it's something that you bring
חלה challah from? דילמא כל קמה קמה, Dilma kol kamah kamah, maybe
anything standing, which would include, like רש״י Rashi says, קטנית, kitnis, like
legumes or something like that. Legumes have the same sense of standing
and tall, but anyway, corn, corn, that's a good point, corn. So
anyway, קמה רחמנא. Kamah Rachmana. No, אתיא קמה קמה. Atya kamah kamah.
כתיב הכא: Ketiv hacha: כי תבא בקמת רעך, Ki tavo beqamat re'echa,
your friend's standing grain, וכתיב התם: uchetiv hatam: מהחל חרמש בקמה. Me'hachel
chermesh bakamah. This is the cutting of the barley for the עומר.
Omer. מה התם קמה דמחייבת בחלה, Mah hatam kamah demichayevet bechallah, the
same way that's one of the grains and you bring חלה challah
from it, אף הכא נמי קמה דמחייבת בחלה, af hacha nami kamah
demichayevet bechallah, here too. So okay, we have vineyard, we have grain,
and we assume that this is grain, not corn or other things.
So maybe only those things where there's special gifts that are given
from it. איכא למפרך: Ika lemafrach: מה לקמה שכן חייבת בחלה? Mah
lekamah shekein chayavat bechallah? Maybe it's limited to קמה kamah where you
give חלה challah from it. No, כרם יוכיח. kerem yochiach. No, it's
not about חלה challah because you give from the vineyard. מה לכרם
שכן חייב בעוללות? Mah lekerem shekein chayav be'olelot? Maybe that's unique because
you give the special thing of עוללות olelot to the poor. קמה
תוכיח. Kamah tochiach. No, that's not true, קמה kamah you don't give
that gift. וחזר הדין, Vechazar hadin, it goes back and forth. לא
ראי זה כראי זה, Lo re'i zeh kire'i zeh, each one's unique
feature is not like the other. הצד השווה שבהן hatzad hashaveh shebahen
is the common denominator, שכן דבר שגידולו קרקע, sheken davar shegidulo karka,
it grows, ובשעת גמר מלאכה פועל אוכל בו, ubishas gmar melacha poel
ochel bo, and when you do the final labor the worker can
eat, אף כל דבר שגידולו קרקע בשעת גמר מלאכה פועל אוכל בו.
af kol davar shegidulo karka bishas gmar melacha poel ochel bo. So
we'll abstract it and that's how we generalize it. So the גמרא
Gemara isn't done. One minute says the גמרא: Gemara: מה להצד השווה
שבהן שכן יש בהן צד מזבח? mah lehatzad hashaveh shebahen sheken yesh
bahen tzad mizbeach? Both corn, both wheat and grapes, something is given
to the מזבח: mizbeach: wine and flour. Okay, so maybe it only
applies to types of produce that you give to the מזבח. mizbeach.
ואתא נמי זית, ve'asa nami zayis, so that would include olives, דאית
ביה צד מזבח de'is bei tzad mizbeach because oil is used for
the, you know, a מנחה. mincha. וזית ממה הצד אתי, vezayis mimah
hatzad asi, that will extrapolate from the common denominator who—so—oh, I'm sorry,
period. So maybe that will include but we won't include everything. So
the גמרא Gemara says בזית ממה הצד אתי? bezayis mimah hatzad asi?
But you want to say that's what you extrapolate, the idea of
olives? הוא גופיה כרם איקרי. hu gufei kerem ikri. We know that
it itself is included in כרם. kerem. Olives are called a כרם.
kerem. דכתיב dichtiv ויבער מגדיש ועד קמה ועד כרם זית, vayaver migadish
ve'ad kama ve'ad kerem zayis, until a vineyard of olives or a
כרם kerem of olives. Right. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, right,
כרם זית איקרי. kerem zayis ikri. It's called a כרם kerem of
olives. כרם סתם לא איקרי, kerem stam lo ikri, but not a
סתם כרם. stam kerem. סתם כרם stam kerem means a vineyard. So
the גמרא Gemara is saying you have a vineyard of grapes, you
have standing grain of wheat, you can infer olives, but how do
you know to go beyond olives, something that isn't brought to the
מזבח? mizbeach? So מכל מקום קשיא, mikol makom kashya, how do you
know to go beyond olives? אלא אמר שמואל אמר קרא ela amar
Shmuel amar kra ובחרמש. ubachermesh. It says do not bring your sickle
to cut it down. לרבות כל בעלי חרמש, lerabos kol ba'alei chermesh,
anything that would have a sickle brought to it, which would include
things like corn, I know they didn't have corn or whatever, but
things that are not just brought to the מזבח. mizbeach. So the
גמרא—one Gemara minute, you can't use חרמש chermesh to include all types
of produce. We need it to tell me something else. בשעת חרמש
תאכל, bishas chermesh tochal, you can only eat while you're doing the
harvesting, like while the sickle is being brought, שלא בשעת חרמש לא
תאכל. shelo bishas chermesh lo sochal. The idea we said earlier, that
it can only be done during the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha as
you are doing the final process. גמרא Gemara says no, that we
know from elsewhere. ההוא מואל כליך לא תתן נפקא. hahu me'el kelecha
lo siten nafka. Don't put it into your vessel. Meaning don't put
it into your vessel because whose vessel are you supposed to be
putting it into? The owner's vessel. So from that we infer that
we're talking about the time when you're doing the גמר מלאכה. gmar
melacha. So we don't need חרמש chermesh to tell me the time
you're doing the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha because we infer it from
the idea you're putting it in your own vessel and not yours.
So חרמש chermesh is telling me it
applies to all produce, not
just produce that goes on
the מזבח. mizbeach.
So now the גמרא Gemara has one last question. תינח דבר חרמש.
tenach debar chermesh. That includes things that
you would bring a sickle to. דלאו בר חרמש מנלן? delav bar
chermesh menalan? How about things you don't bring a sickle to? אלא
אמר רב יצחק אמר קרא קמה, ela amar Rav Yitzchak amar kra
kama, standing. לרבות כל בעלי קמה, lerabos kol ba'alei kama, anything that
grows. So the גמרא Gemara says how can you say that? והאמרת
קמה קמה דמחייבא בחלה. veha'amarta kama kama demichayva bechallah. You said קמה
kama only includes grain that you bring חלה challah from. How can
you say the word קמה kama now means anything that grows? הני
מילי מקמי דניתי חרמש. hani mili mikamei denaysi chermesh. That was before
we had חרמש chermesh to broaden it, to say to include anything
that you bring a sickle to. השתא דאתי חרמש, hashta de'asi chermesh,
now that חרמש chermesh includes anything you bring a sickle to, it's
not limited to things that you make חלה challah from. It includes
even like קטניות kitniyos or whatever. So once it's not limited to
things you bring חלה challah from, what does the word קמה kama
mean? איתרבי ליה כל דבר חרמש. israbei leh kol davar chermesh. We
learned to include anything you bring a sickle to, ואף על גב
דלא מחייבא בחלה, ve'af al gav delo michayva bechallah, even though you
don't bring חלה challah from it. So therefore קמה למה לי? kama
lamah li? So what does קמה kama include? לאתויי לרבות כל בעלי
קמה, la'asuyei lerabos kol ba'alei kama, anything that grows. Okay, so that
was, phew, a long—I did that pretty quickly, but the basic point
was, okay, that we learned the idea that it's limited to the
time of doing the actual גמר מלאכה gmar melacha from the ואל
כליך לא תתן. ve'el kelecha lo siten. And we learned from the
idea that it's talking about כרם kerem and wheat, and then we
generalized. But how do you really broaden it to everything? Well, on
the one hand, חרמש chermesh tells you anything you bring a sickle
to. Once חרמש chermesh tells me anything you bring a sickle to,
it's not limited to things that go on the מזבח. mizbeach. Once
it's not limited to things that go on the מזבח, mizbeach, the
word קמה kama standing means anything that stands, anything that grows. It
doesn't just mean wheat because we know it's not limited to those
types of things. So then the word קמה kama in that context
means anything that grows. So we now generalize anything that's grown at
the time of the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha you are entitled to
eat, and we will pick up with this tomorrow. All right, thank
you for staying a little later. See you for Sunday. Schedule for
Sunday. Oh, for you, yeah.